Haipeng Yu January 2022

CONTACT Information

239B Kildee Hall Iowa State University Ames, Iowa 50011 USA E-mail: hpyu@iastate.edu Phone: (701) 730-1368 WWW: haipengu.github.io

# RESEARCH INTERESTS

My research interests focus on integrating high-dimensional heterogeneous data to advance genetic improvements in agriculture. Particularly, I am interested in accommodating multi-omics data into genetic evaluations of animals and plants using statistical modeling, machine learning, and computational methods. I am also interested in applying computer vision to collect real-time animal activity data and incorporating the sensor data into my research using machine learning and statistical modeling.

#### **EDUCATION**

## Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA

Ph.D., Animal and Poultry Sciences - Quantitative Genetics, May 2020

- Dissertation: "Designing and modeling high-throughput phenotyping data in quantitative genetics" [Virginia Tech Libraries]
- Advisor: Dr. Gota Morota

#### North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA

M.S., Animal Sciences - Animal Breeding and Genetics, August 2016

- Thesis: "The exploration of a four-platform standing scale in the application of measuring temperament in beef cattle"
- Advisor: Dr. Lauren Hulsman Hanna

#### Qingdao Agricultural University, Qingdao, Shandong CHINA

B.S., Veterinary Medicine, July 2013

# Professional Positions

#### Iowa State University, Ames, Iowa USA

Post-doctoral Fellow

08/2020 - Present

• Advisors: Drs. Jack Dekkers and Rohan Fernando

## Work Experience

Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences

### Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia USA

• Graduate Research Assistant

08/2018 - 05/2020

• Graduate Teaching Assistant

Spring 2019 and Spring 2020

Department of Animal Science

### University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, Nebraska USA

• Graduate Research Assistant

08/2016 - 08/2018

#### Department of Animal Sciences

#### North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA

• Graduate Teaching Assistant

08/2015 - 05/2016

• Graduate Research Assistant

01/2015 - 05/2016

### Professional society memberships

- American Dairy Science Association. 2021 Present
- American Society of Animal Science. 2017 Present

### EDITORIAL ACTIVITIES

#### Ad Hoc Reviewer

• Number of manuscripts reviewed per journal: BMC Plant Biology (1), Frontiers in Animal Science (1), Journal of Animal Science (4), Scientific Reports (1), The Plant Genome (1)

# PEER REVIEWED JOURNAL ARTICLES

6 first author and 5 co-author

2021

- 11. Clevinger EM, Biyashev R, Lerch-Olson E, <u>Yu H</u>, Quigley C, Song Q, Dorrance AE, Robertson AE, and Maroof S. Identification of Quantitative Disease Resistance Loci towards Four Pythium Species in Soybean. *Frontiers in Plant Science*. doi: 10.3389/fpls.2021.644746
- 10. Pegolo S, <u>Yu H</u>, Morota G, Bisutti V, Rosa GJM, Bittante G, and Cecchinato A. Structural equation modelling for unravelling the multivariate genomic architecture of milk proteins in dairy cattle. *Journal of Dairy Science*. doi: 10.3168/jds.2020-18321
- Yu H and Morota G. GCA: An R package for genetic connectedness analysis using pedigree and genomic data. BMC Genomics. 22:119. doi: 10.1186/s12864-021-07414-7
- 8. <u>Yu H</u>, Lee K, and Morota G. Forecasting dynamic body weight of non-restrained pigs from images using an RGB-D sensor camera. *Translational Animal Science*. **5**:1-9. doi: 10.1093/tas/txab006
- 7. Momen M, Bhatta M, Hussain W, Yu H, and Morota G. Modeling multiple phenotypes in wheat using data-driven genomic exploratory factor analysis and Bayesian network learning. *Plant Direct.* **00**:e00304. doi: 10.1002/pld3.304

2020

- 6. Amorim ST, <u>Yu H</u>, Momen M, de Albuquerque, LG, Pereira, ASC, Baldi F, and Morota G. An assessment of genomic connectedness measures in Nellore cattle. *Journal of Animal Science*. 98:1-12. doi: 10.1093/jas/skaa289
- 5. Yu H, Morota G, Celestino EF, Dahlen CR, Wagner SA, Riley DG, and Hanna LLH. Deciphering cattle temperament measures derived from a four-platform standing scale using genetic factor analytic modeling. Frontiers in Genetics. 11:599. doi: 10.3389/fgene.2020.00599

2019

4. Hanna LLH, Hieber JK, <u>Yu H</u>, Celestino Jr EF, Dahlen CR, Wagner SA, and Riley DG. Blood collection has negligible impact on scoring temperament in Angus-based weaned calves. *Livestock Science*. **230**:103835. doi: 10.1016/j.livsci.2019.103835

3. Yu H, Campbell MT, Zhang Q, Walia H, and Morota G. Genomic Bayesian confirmatory factor analysis and Bayesian network to characterize a wide spectrum of rice phenotypes. G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics. 9:1975-1986. doi: 10.1534/g3.119.400154

2018

 Yu H, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. Do stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units? *Journal of Animal Science*. 96:4490-4500. doi: 10.1093/jas/sky316

2017

1. <u>Yu H</u>, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. Genomic relatedness strengthens genetic connectedness across management units. *G3: Genes, Genomes, Genetics.* **10**:3543-3556. doi: 10.1534/g3.117.300151

### PEER REVIEWED CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

1 first author

2018

Yu H, Spangler ML, Lewis RM, and Morota G. 2018. Stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units. In: *Proceedings*, 11th World Congress of Genetics Applied to Livestock Production. 11:406. February 11-16, Auckland, New Zealand. [PDF]

BIORXIVED
MANUSCRIPTS

 Campbell M, Yu H, Momen M, and Morota G. Examining the relationships between phenotypic plasticity and local environments with genomic structural equation models. bioRxiv. doi: 10.1101/2019.12.11.873257

# INVITED PRESENTATIONS

2022

1. Bayesian hierarchical inference to integrate a nutritional growth model into genomic evaluation of pigs. Feed Platform Meeting. Topigs Norsvin. Online. April 21.

# CONTRIBUTED PRESENTATIONS

2021

7. A Bayesian hierarchical model to integrate growth models into genomic evaluation of pigs. ASAS-CSAS-SSASAS Annual Meeting and Trade Show. Online. July 14-23.

2020

- **6**. Development of image analysis pipeline to predict body weight in pigs. EAAP Annual Meeting 2020. Online. December 3.
- 5. Development of image analysis pipeline to predict body weight in pigs. ASAS-CSAS-WSASAS Virtual Annual Meeting and Trade Show. Online. July 19-23.

2019

4. Precision agriculture on cattle temperament: Utilizing factor analysis and multi-trait modeling to characterize a four-platform standing scale. NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. Blacksburg, VA. October 10-11.

2018 3. An assessment of genomic relatedness across management units. ADSA-ASAS 2018 Midwest Meeting. Omaha, NE. March 12-14. 2017 2. Stronger measures of genomic connectedness enhance prediction accuracies across management units. NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. Stanley Stout Livestock Marketing Center, Manhattan, KS. October 18-19. 1. Genomic relatedness strengthens genetic connectedness across management units. ASAS-CSAS Annual Meeting and Trade Show. Baltimore, MD. July 8-12. Intramural SEMINARS 2021 • Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, Iowa State University. September 3. 2020 • Animal Breeding and Genetics Graduate Student Organization seminar. Department of Animal Science, Iowa State University. October 2. • Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, Iowa State University. September 18. • Ph.D. Thesis Defense. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. March 18. 2019 • Ninth Annual Animal and Poultry Sciences Research Symposium. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. May 21. • The Reproductive Biology Club. Department of Animal and Poultry Sciences, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. April 19. 2018 • Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. February 28. 2017 Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, University of Nebraska-

2017 • A

- Animal Breeding and Genetics seminar. Department of Animal Science, University of Nebraska Lincoln. February 14.
- Animal Breeding and Genetics Seminars. Department of Animal Sciences, University of Nebraska-Lincoln. September 29.

• M.S. Thesis Defense. Department of Animal Sciences, North Dakota State University. May 17.

Teaching

2016

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Virginia, USA

Guest Instructor

• GWAS Workshop [Slides]

**Summer 2019** 

Graduate Teaching Assistant

• APSC 5984/20816: Complex Trait Genomics [WWW]

• ALS 3104: Animal Breeding and Genetics Spring 2019

Tutorials

- Factor Analytic Model [WWW]
- Gaussian Bayesian Network [WWW]
- Structural Equation Model GWAS [WWW]

#### University of Nebraska-Lincoln, Lincoln, Nebraska, USA

#### Guest Instructor

• ASCI 944 / STAT 844 Quantitative Methods for Genomics of Complex Traits Spring 2018 [Slides] [WWW]

# North Dakota State University, Fargo, North Dakota USA

Graduate Teaching Assistant

• ANSC 357: Animal Genetics

Spring 2016

Spring 2020

• AGRI 189: Skills for Academic Success

Fall 2015

# SOFTWARE DEVELOPMENTS

#### R package

• GCA - https://github.com/HaipengU/GCA

PARTICIPATION IN MEETINGS, SYMPOSIUMS, AND WORKSHOPS

2021

• Poultry Breeder's Roundtable & National Swine Improvement Federation Joint Meeting. Marriott St. Louis Grand, St. Louis, MO. November 30 - December 2.

2020

- The 6th International Conference of Quantitative Genetics. Online. November 2-12.
- The Plant and Animal Genome XXVIII Conference. Town and Country Hotel, San Diego, CA. January 11-15.

2015

- NCERA-225 Annual Meeting. Implementation and Strategies for National Beef Cattle Genetic Evaluation. North Dakota State University, ND. October 22-23.
- Graduate Learning Conference for College Teaching. North Dakota State University, ND. August 17-18.
- WERA-1: Beef Cattle Breeding in the Western Region. Miles City, MT. May 19-20.
- ADSA-ASAS Midwest Meeting. Des Moines, IA. March 15-18.

Honors/ Awards

2020 • The 6th International Conference of Quantitative Genetics US-Based Early Career Researcher Scholarship. Online. November. 2019 • 24th Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics (SISG) Scholarship, University of Washington, Seattle, WA, July. • Ninth Annual Animal and Poultry Sciences Research Symposium Travel Award \$400, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, May. 2015• Frank Bain Graduate Student Scholarship \$1,650, North Dakota State University, Spring. • Outstanding Undergraduate Scholarship, Qingdao Agricultural University, China. 2009-2013 Additional TRAINING 2019 • Deep Learning for Computer Vision Workshop, Virginia Tech, VA, September 6. • 24th Summer Institute in Statistical Genetics (SISG), University of Washington, Seattle, WA, July 17-24. 2018 • Programming and Computer Algorithms in Animal Breeding With Focus on Genomic Selection and Single-Step GBLUP, University of Georgia, GA, May 7-25. 2017• Introduction to Graphical Models With Applications to Quantitative Genetics and Genomics, Iowa State University, IA, June 19-23.

• Software Carpentry Workshop. University of Nebraska-Lincoln, NE, January 5-6.